From above the world of Cars
Planes is a animation, family, adventure film directed by Klay Hall.
Dusty is a cropdusting plane who dreams of competing in a famous aerial race.
The problem?
He is hopelessly afraid of heights.
With the support of his mentor Skipper and a host of new
friends, Dusty sets off to make his dreams come true.
Dusty Crophopper (voice), played by Dane Cook.
El Chupacabra (voice), played by Carlos Alazraqui.
Bravo (voice), played by Val Kilmer.
Rochelle (voice), played by Julia Louis-Dreyfus.
Chug (voice), played by Brad Garrett.
Dottie (voice), played by Teri Hatcher.
Planes is a 2013 American animated sports comedy film produced by
Disneytoon Studios, and a spin-off of Pixar's Cars franchise.
The film stars the voices of Dane Cook, Stacy Keach, Priyanka Chopra,  Teri Hatcher, Brad Garrett, Julia
Louis-Dreyfus, Roger Craig Smith, John Cleese, Carlos Alazraqui, Anthony Edwards, Sinbad, and Val Kilmer.
In the film, Dusty Crophopper, a crop duster plane in the town of Propwash Junction, wants to complete the Wings Around
the Globe racing challenge, despite his fear of heights, with the help of naval aviator Skipper Riley.
The film was directed by Klay Hall and written by Jeffrey M.
In developing a concept created by John Lasseter, the writers made a conscious effort to avoid remaking Cars in a
new setting, while reusing Keach and Danny Mann's characters from the Cars Toons short "Air Mater".
The production team conducted research by interviewing several
pilots of plane types that were included in the movie.
Jon Cryer was initially announced as the voice of
Dusty, before being replaced by Cook.
Despite dropping out, Cryer received credit on the
film for "additional story material".
The musical score was composed by Mark Mancina, while Prana Studios
provided work on visual effects, animation and compositing.
Planes premiered on August 2, 2013, at EAA AirVenture
Oshkosh, a gathering of aviation enthusiasts.
It was initially intended to be released as a direct-to-video film, but
was instead released theatrically on August 9, 2013.
It received generally negative reviews from critics and
grossed $240 million against a $50 million budget.
A sequel, Planes: Fire & Rescue, was released in 2014.
The film explores themes of countryside, sports,
competition, training, crop duster.
The tone is lighthearted.